Finding Aid for Leslie Kish Papers 1952-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leslie Kish Papers 1952-2001
Kish, Leslie, 1910-
6 linear feet
Sociologist, a founder of the University of Michigan Institute for Social Research, specialist in scientific population sampling. Biographical and autobiographical information; including some details on service with Abraham Lincoln Brigade; University of Michigan administrative files; department of sociology course materials; files relating to summer programs in sampling techniques for foreign statisticians; papers on sampling and related topics; files from his association with the Institute for Social Research; organizational files and correspondence.
0269 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library from the Kish family in 2000 and 2001. Donor no. 9035
The collection is open for research.
Leslie Kish was born in 1910 in Poprad, then part of the Austro-Hungarian Empire, now in Slovakia. He emigrated to the United with his family in 1925. In 1937, concerned about the threat of a fascist sweep through Europe, Kish volunteered with the International Brigade to fight the Spanish Loyalists.
He returned home in 1939 and graduated Phi Beta Kappa from the City College of New York with a degree in mathematics. He then moved to Washington DC, when he was employed first at the US Census Bureau, then at the US Department of Agriculture, where he joined a group of social scientists, including psychologist Rensis Likert, who were creating a survey research unit within the department. Again, his career was interrupted by a war. In 1942-1945, he served in the US Army Air Corps as a meteorologist.
In 1947, Kish moved to the University of Michigan with Likert and others, to found the Institute for Social Research, the world's largest academic survey and research organization. One of the programs that he initiated for the institute was the Sampling Program for Foreign Statisticians offered in the summer and that now has two generations of alumni in more that 100 countries. During his early years at Michigan, Kish combined full time statistical work with the completion of an MA in mathematical statistics in 1948 and a Ph.D. in sociology in 1952.
The superiority of the sampling techniques that he developed was first established in the 1948 US presidential election. A small national probability sample of less than 1000 US households drawn by Kish and his Michigan colleagues showed Dewey and Truman running very close together, with Truman in a slight lead, while commercial polls and the press predicted a Dewey landslide. Kish was also one of the first proponents of an annual rolling sampling, such as the American Community Survey, scheduled to replace the long form of the US decennial census by 2010.
Kish was widely recognized as one of the world's leading experts on scientific population sampling, and received many honors and awards during his career. He was named a Russel Lecturer and elected president of the American Statistical Association. He also was elected a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the Royal Statistical Society of England. His 1965 book, Survey Sampling, is still used around the world.
Kish's scholarly writing and innovative research continued after his formal retirement in 1981. He traveled extensively, consulting on sampling and multinational survey design with colleagues in the US and around the world. He was elected an honorary member of the International Statistical Institute and the Hungarian Academy of Sciences, and received an honorary doctorate from the University of Bologna, Italy, on the occasion of its 900th anniversary.
Leslie Kish died on October 7, 2000 in Ann Arbor at age 90.
Note: This biography was excerpted from The University Record, October 16, 2000.
The papers of Professor Leslie Kish relate primarily to his activities as a university professor and to his research interests. Included as well is an extensive run of his various writings. The papers date from 1952 to 2001 and are divided into six series: Biographical Information, University of Michigan Administrative and Course Materials, Papers and Presentations, Institute of Social Research, Organizations and Activities, and Personal and Professional Correspondence.
Subjects:
Kish, Leslie, 1910-2000.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV.; Sampling (Statistics); Social sciences--Statistical methods.; Social surveys.; Sociology--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Kish, Leslie, 1910-2000.; Sampling (Statistics); Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series contains Leslie Kish's vita, an interview published in 1996 and autobiographical information. A video prepared by the University of Michigan BMC Media is also included in this series.
  - Videocassette: "Reflections by Leslie Kish on a Lifetime of Survey Sampling," 2001, VHS videocassette (Box 1)
  - Biographical information and Vita (Box 1)
  - Article: "A conversation with Leslie Kish" by Martin Frankel and Benjamin King 1996 (Box 1)
  - Autobiography: "Chapters from the life of Leslie Kish," undated (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Administrative and Course Materials
  The University of Michigan Administrative and Course Materials series contains information related to the courses that Kish offered at the University of Michigan. It also includes information about the Sampling Program for Foreign Statisticians that he initiated at the Institute of Social Research. Photographs of this program are included in this series. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Administrative Information
    - Department of Sociology
      - Correspondence
        - Courses and Program 1952-1957, 1964-1968, 1972-1973, 1976 (Box 1)
        - Faculty 1983, 1988, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1975-1978 (Box 1)
      - The Revitalized Professional MA Degree 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Experiments and Studies in Statistics 1973, 1976, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Program in Biostatistics 1976-1979, 1980, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Students Research Assistants 1974, 1975, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Internationalization of the University Group 1988 (Box 1)
    - Master Degree in Statistics with a Sociology Option 1967, 1971-1976, 1980, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: PhDs in Sciences for Grades 9-12 1996 (Box 1)
    - Social Statistics MA Program (Box 1)
  - Course Materials
    - Computer Programs
      - ABSERD undated (Box 1)
      - PSALMS undated (Box 1)
    - Course Offerings 1956-1958, 1968, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Freshman Seminar: "Chance, Life and Risk," 1981 (Box 1)
    - Psych. 234: Theory of Sampling Surveys 1948 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 612: Methods of Survey Sampling
      - Course Description 1964-1965, 1971, 1974-1978, 1980 (Box 1)
      - Exams and Problems 1971, 1976-1978, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 613: Advanced Methods of Survey Sampling 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 614: Study Designs in Survey Research 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 621: Workshop in Sampling Techniques 1976, 1979, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 630: Research Methods in Population and Human Ecology 1964 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 710: Statistical Research Design 1970, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
    - Sociology 717: Methods and Theory of Sample Design 1963, 1968, 1970-1971, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Other Programs
    - Summer Institute in Survey Research Techniques
      - Directories 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Evaluations 1948, 1953, 1956, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Sampling Program for Foreign Statisticians
      - Program Description undated (Box 1)
      - Student's' Directories 1961-1978, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
      - Funding
        - Ford Foundation 1965-1980, 4 folders (Box 1)
        - Various Sources of Support 1971, 1974-1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Photographs: Group portraits of participants
        - 1966, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
        - 1975-1981 (Box 2)
      - Reports 1979-1983 (Box 2)
      - Students
        - Correspondence Regarding Students from Latin America 1961-1965 (Box 2)
        - Abuzar Asra, Indonesia 1978 (Box 2)
        - Eduardo Borja, Ecuador, and Mohamed Omer Dubed, Somali 1979 (Box 2)
        - J.P. Banda, Zambia 1975-1979 (Box 2)
        - Students' Survival Kit 1974-1975, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Information 1977 (Box 2)
      - Sampling Program for Statisticians from Underdeveloped Countries 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Summer Institute in Survey Sampling in Latin America
      - Program Description 1971 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence
        - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
        - 1970, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Workshop in Practical Problems of Survey Sampling for Central America, Mexico City 1976-1976 (Box 2)
- Papers and Presentations
  The Papers and Presentations series is arranged alphabetically and contains a wide variety of papers written by Kish about different topics in statistics, including his Ph.D. dissertation in 1952, "On the Differentiation of Ecological Units."
  - Book Reviews by Leslie Kish undated (Box 2)
  - Titled Papers
    - "Cumulating/Combining Population Surveys," 1999 (Box 2)
    - "Developing Samplers for Developing Countries," 1995 (Box 2)
    - "Hundred Years of Survey Sampling," 1997 (Box 2)
    - "Large Scale Multipurpose Survey Sampling Errors," 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Modular Design for Comparisons," 1978 (Box 2)
    - "Multipurpose Sample Designs," 1987 (Box 2)
    - "On the Differentiation of Ecological Units," 1952 (Box 2)
      (Leslie Kish Thesis)
    - "Randomization of Subjects over Treatments and over Populations," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Repetitiousness and Variability of Consumer Behavior," 1958 (Box 2)
    - "Sampling," 1998 (Box 2)
    - "Sampling Employers with Probabilities to a Measure Size," undated (Box 2)
    - "Sampling Methods for Agricultural Surveys," 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Sampling Methods for Demography," 1980 (Box 2)
    - "Some Efficient Random Imputation Methods," undated (Box 2)
    - "Space/Time Variations in Survey Estimates," 1995 (Box 2)
    - "Special Aspects of Demographics Samples," undated (Box 2)
    - "Statistics for Correlated Selections," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Reflections on Survey Sampling and New Directions," 1992 (Box 2)
    - "Weighting: Why, When and How?," 2000 (Box 2)
  - Multiple Papers and Background Material on Various Topics
    - Censuses
      - 1979-1983, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
      - 1990, 1993-1994, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Demographic Sampling 1980 (Box 2)
    - Designs for Comparisons 1973 (Box 2)
    - Falsifiability 1987 (Box 2)
    - Imputation 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Multipopulation Statistics 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - Multivariate Analysis 1956 (Box 2)
    - Population Surveys 1958, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Quota Sampling
      - 1998 (Box 2)
      - undated (Box 2)
    - Respondent Selection undated (Box 2)
    - Sampling Errors 1955-1956, 1968, 1871-1975 (Box 2)
    - Sampling Methods undated (Box 2)
    - Social Indicators 1972, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Statistics in China 1982, 1990, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Variance Computations undated (Box 3)
    - Articles written for "Survey Statistician," 1978-1981, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Various Topics
      - 1956-1961, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1970-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1980-1985, 1988, 1992 (Box 3)
      - undated (Box 3)
  - Presentations given before professional organizations
    - Discussion on Conceptual and Theoretical Framework for Survey Sampling 1981 (Box 3)
    - International Statistic Institute Sessions 1981-1983, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Lectures in London 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Lectures in Quito, Ecuador 1970-1975, 1979, 1983-1988 (Box 3)
    - "Multi-city Area Samples for China," 1996 (Box 3)
    - "On the Gap Between Mathematical Statistics and Survey Sampling," 1994 (Box 3)
- Institute of Social Research
  The Institute of Social Research series contains projects and proposals in which Kish and his colleagues worked at the institute. This series is arranged alphabetically. Some of these projects concern studies in economic behavior, electoral issues, and consumer finances studies, among others.
  - Administration
    - Institute of Social Research External Review Committee 1996 (Box 3)
    - Memorandums
      - 1953, 1960-1961, 1968-1974, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      - 1981, 1983, 1985, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Sampling Activities and Procedures at the Survey Research Center undated (Box 3)
  - Funding and Proposals
    - Developmental Proposal 1984 (Box 3)
    - Edgar Stern Family Fund 1961-1966 (Box 3)
    - Funds for Population Research 1957 (Box 3)
    - Grant Proposals
      - National Science Foundation 1965, 1969, 1970-1971, 1981 (Box 3)
      - Various Sources of Support 1971, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Proposal for a Survey on Chinese Perceptions and Preferences Regarding Inequality 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Variance Components of Population Characteristics 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Projects
    - Correspondence regarding projects 1946, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - Detroit Area Study
      - Project Description 1976 (Box 3)
      - A Study in Political Participation 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      - Proposal for Strengthening the Detroit Area Study through a Partnership with SRC 1994 (Box 3)
      - Sampling Errors and Variance Calculations 1952-1953 (Box 3)
      - Selection of a Sample of Dwelling Units 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - Half-day Work Module 1961, 1973 (Box 3)
    - HIV Cost and Services Utilization Study 1994-1998 (Box 4)
    - Morbidity Project 1951 (Box 4)
    - National Crime Survey Redesign 1979 (Box 4)
    - Presidential Voting Study 1956 (Box 4)
    - Projects Supported by the US Bureau of the Census 1975 (Box 4)
    - Sampling Errors Projects
      - 1950-1951, 1954-1955, 1959 (Box 4)
      - 1963-1966 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Sampling Plan for Household Survey in Argentina undated (Box 4)
    - Sampling in Puerto Rico 1952 (Box 4)
    - Standard Sample of Counties 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Studies on Consumer Attitudes and Inclinations to Buy 1963 (Box 4)
    - Suggested Field Procedures 1946, 1948, 1951, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Survey of Consumer Finances 1948, 1950-1957 (Box 4)
    - Survey Sampling Techniques 1977-1986 (Box 4)
    - Telephone Survey Component of the 1984 National Election Studies, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Research Ideas
      - 1951-1952 (Box 4)
      - undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Projects
      - 1943, 1946, 1950, 1954 (Box 4)
      - 1970, 1979, 1981, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Social Research Center Sections
    - Consumer Finances Section 1949-1953 (Box 4)
    - Economic Behavior Program 1950-1953, 1956-1957, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Economic Survey Section 1950, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Sampling Section
      - Administrative Information 1958, 1960-1961, 1968, 1971, 1973, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Studies 1949, 1951-1958 (Box 4)
- Organizational and Other Activities
  The Organizational and Other Activities series is arranged alphabetically and contains information about organizations in which Kish was part. This includes the American Statistical Association, of which he was president and the International Association of Survey Statisticians. This series also contains information that demonstrates the commitment of Leslie Kish to peace. Kish was of the faculty who signed a petition to President Lyndon B. Johnson to stop the bombing in Vietnam.
  - American Statistical Association
    - Correspondence 1987-1989 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Statistics and National/International Security 1987-1991, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Session: "Continuing Education in Statistics," 1975 (Box 4)
  - International Association of Survey Statisticians 1978, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
  - Petition to Stop the Bombing of North Vietnam 1967 (Box 4)
  - Senate Assembly
    - 1968-1972 (Box 4)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - UNESCO Prize for Peace 1990-1994 (Box 4)
- Personal and Professional Correspondence
  - A Correspondence (Box 5)
    - 1978-1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1985-1999, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - B Correspondence 1977-1997, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - C Correspondence
    - 1977-1989 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1995, 1998 (Box 5)
  - China
    - 1983, 1986-1989 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1991, 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - D Correspondence
    - 1977-1981 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1998 (Box 5)
  - E Correspondence 1977-1978, 1980-1988, 1990-1994 (Box 5)
  - F Correspondence
    - 1978-1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985-1990, 1992-1996 (Box 5)
  - G Correspondence 1978-1989, 1991-1992, 1995-1998, 2000 (Box 5)
  - H Correspondence
    - 1978-1988 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1998, 2000 (Box 5)
  - I Correspondence 1978-1981, 1988-1990, 1992, 1995 (Box 5)
  - J Correspondence 1977-1985, 1988-1997 (Box 5)
  - K Correspondence
    - 1978-1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1991-2000 (Box 6)
  - L Correspondence 1979-1999, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - M Correspondence
    - 1977-1984 (Box 6)
    - 1985-1992, 1995-2000 (Box 6)
  - N Correspondence 1978-1989, 1991, 1994-1997 (Box 6)
  - O Correspondence 1979-1981, 1988, 1990, 1993, 1996, 1998 (Box 6)
  - P, Q Correspondence 1976-1996 (Box 6)
  - R Correspondence 1978-2000, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - S Correspondence 1977-2000, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - T Correspondence
    - 1975-1979 (Box 6)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1991-1997, 2000 (Box 6)
  - U and V Correspondence 1978-1982, 1985-1988, 1990-1997 (Box 6)
  - W Correspondence
    - 1974-1979 (Box 6)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 6)
  - X, Y Z Correspondence 1978-1984, 1987, 1991, 1995-2000 (Box 6)